Ludwig Sander
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ludwig Sander papers
1910-1975
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ludwig Sander
2.8 linear feet
The papers of American New York School painter Ludwig Sander measure 2.8 linear feet and date from 1910 to 1975. Found are biographical materials primarily consisting of army records; correspondence with family and colleagues discussing exhibitions and other art-related activities; diaries; personal scattered business records; address books and art history typescripts; sketchbooks and illustrations for magazines; photographs of Sander, his colleagues, his travels, and exhibition openings; and miscellaneous printed material. The collection documents Sander's career and interactions with some of the most important modern artists of twentieth century.
Biographical Note
American painter Ludwig Sander was born on July 18, 1906 in Staten Island, New York. After independent studies with Boardman Robinson and Alexander Archipenko, he attended the Art Students' League from 1928 to 1930. From 1931 to 1932, Sander studied art in Paris and with Hans Hofmann in Munich. While in Europe, he befriended many other artists including Balcomb Greene, Reuben Nakian, and Vaclav Vytlacil.
After Army service from 1942 to 1945, Sander returned to school, earning a B.A. in Art History from New York University in 1952. He taught at various schools including the Art Students' League, the School of Visual Art, and the University of Pennsylvania. He was also a charter member of The Club, a postwar group of New York artists famous for its polemic discussions.
From 1959, Sander regularly exhibited his art work and had solo exhibitions at prominent galleries including the Leo Castelli Gallery, Kootz Gallery, and the Knoedler Gallery. His work is in the permanent collections of the Art Institute of Chicago, the Guggenheim Museum, and the Whitney Museum of American Art.
Ludwig Sander died July 3, 1975 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of American New York School painter Ludwig Sander measure 2.8 linear feet and date from 1910 to 1975. Found within the collection are biographical materials primarily consisting of army records; correspondence with family and colleagues discussing exhibitions and other art-related activities; diaries containing brief annotations of daily activities; personal business records including studio leases, teaching contracts, and miscellaneous receipts; notes and writings including address books and art history typescripts; art work consisting primarily of sketchbooks and illustrations for magazines; photographs of Sander, his colleagues, his travels, and exhibition openings; and miscellaneous printed material. The collection Sander's career and interactions with some of the most important artists of 20th century modern art.
Chronological correspondence primarily consists of letters from Sanders to his mother during his army service, and letters from his colleagues discussing exhibitions and other art-related activities. Correspondents include Clement Greenberg, Philip Guston, Yvonne Hagen, Gottfried Honegger, Sam Kootz, and Vaclav Vytlacil. There are single letters from Georgi Daskaloff, Philip Johnson, Richard Neutra, George Plimpton, and Maximilian Schell, and an invitation to a croquet party from Willem and Elaine De Kooning, Sander, Nancy Ward, and Franz Kline.
Arrangement
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1927-1969 (Box 1, 4; 9 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1931-1975 (Box 1; 28 folders)
Series 3: Diaries, 1931-1973 (Box 1; 11 folders)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1953-1974, undated (Box 2; 4 folders)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, 1951-1960, undated (Box 2; 8 folders)
Series 6: Art Work, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 2, 4; 18 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1910-1973, undated (Box 2, 4; 34 folders)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1926-1975, undated (Box 2-5; 30 folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Castelli, Leo; Kline, Franz, 1910-1962; Kootz, Samuel Melvin, 1898-1982; Lassaw, Ibram, 1913-; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-; Vytlacil, Vaclav, 1892-1984
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Sketches; Sketchbooks; Photographs; Exhibition catalogs
Names:
De Kooning, Willem, 1904-; Guston, Philip, 1913-; Hagen, Yvonne; Honegger, Gottfried, 1917-; De Kooning, Elaine
Provenance
The Ludwig Sander papers were donated by the artist's widow, Kate Sander, in 1975. Ludwig Sander loaned printed material for microfilming in 1970, and it is available on Reel 32.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 5900-5902. Earlier loaned material was microfilmed on Reel 32. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1927-1969, Series 1:; (Box 1, 4; 9 folders)
  Biographical material primarily consists of army records documenting Sander's service during World War II. School records reflect his studies in Europe and at New York University, and include a student identity card signed by Hans Hofmann. Also included are curriculum vitae and passports.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Reel 5900)
  - Passports, 1927-1964, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5900)
  - School Records, 1931-1952 (Box 1, Reel 5900)
  - Army Records, 1940-1950, (4 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5900)
  - Membership Cards, 1962, undated (Box 1, Reel 5900)
  - Oversized Training Certificate, 1944 (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5900)
- Correspondence, 1931-1975, Series 2:; (Box 1; 28 folders)
  Chronological correspondence primarily consists of letters from Sanders to his mother during his army service, and letters from his colleagues discussing exhibitions and other art-related activities. Correspondents include Clement Greenberg, Philip Guston, Yvonne Hagen, Gottfried Honegger, Sam Kootz, and Vaclav Vytlacil. There are single letters from Georgi Daskaloff, Philip Johnson, Richard Neutra, George Plimpton, and Maximilian Schell, and an invitation to a croquet party from Willem and Elaine De Kooning, Sander, Nancy Ward, and Franz Kline.
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1931-1975, (28 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5900)
- Diaries, 1931-1973, Series 3:; (Box 1; 11 folders)
  Eighteen diaries contain very brief annotations describing daily activities. There are two diaries each for years 1961, 1962, and 1964. Four of the diaries also contain listings of addresses.
  - Diaries, 1931-1964, (6 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5900)
  - Diaries, 1965-1973, (5 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5901)
- Personal Business Records, 1953-1974, undated, Series 4:; (Box 2; 4 folders)
  Personal Business Records consist of leases for lofts in New York and contracts for teaching and for recorded interviews. There are also miscellaneous receipts, primarily for art supplies and travel expenses.
  - Leases, 1953 (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Contracts, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Receipts for Art Supplies, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1967-1970, undated (Box 2, Reel 5901)
- Notes and Writings, 1951-1960, undated, Series 5:; (Box 2; 8 folders)
  Notes consist of address books and lists. Writings include typescripts about Vermeer and an artist's statement by Sander and typescripts about Sander by others.
  - Address Books, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - List of Artists'Addresses Possibly for The Club, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Typescripts by Sander, 1951-1952, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Artist's Statement by Sander, 1960 (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Typescripts about Sander by Others, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5901)
- Art Work, circa 1930s-1970s, Series 6:; (Box 2, 4; 18 folders)
  Art work consists primarily of sketchbooks, at least two of which are from his European travels. The majority of the illustrations were made for Encore magazine.
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1930s-1970s, (8 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5901)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1930s-1970s, (4 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Illustrations for Magazines, circa 1930s-1970s, (5 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches and Watercolors, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Two Oversize Sketchbooks, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5902)
  - Oversize Watercolor, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5902)
- Photographs, 1910-1973, undated, Series 7:; (Box 2, 4; 34 folders)
  Photographs of Sander include one with his mother and several with his Army company. Photographs of exhibition openings include James Brooks, Clement Greenberg, Conrad Marca-Relli, Esteban Vicente, and Hugo Weber. Photographs of Sander with colleagues include Leo Castelli, Elaine De Kooning, Willem De Kooning, and Harold Rosenberg. This subseries sometimes includes related photographs of their surroundings from the same roll of film. There are also miscellaneous travel photographs.
  - Photographs of Sander, 1910-1973, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Photographs of Exhibition Openings, 1958-1964, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Photographs of Sander with Colleagues, 1924-1969, (23 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Photographs of Summer Home at Sagapanack, Long Island, 1961, undated (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Photographs of Art Work by Sander, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Travel Photographs, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Oversize Photograph of Sander with Willem De Kooning and Balcomb Greene, 1964 (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5902)
- Printed Material, 1926-1975, undated, Series 8:; (Box 2-5; 30 folders)
  - Clippings, 1940-1975, (6 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5902)
  - Clippings and Galleys of Encore Magazine Illustrated by Sander, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Clippings from Tomorrow Magazine Illustrated by Sander, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Press Releases, 1963, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Brochure for Art Students' League, 1926-1927 (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Sander, 1951-1975, undated, (13 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1970, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Brochures for Colorado College, 1951-1953 (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Brochures for Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center School, 1951-1954 (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Programs, 1962-1970 (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Reproductions of Art Work by Others, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Picture Postcards, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1939-1971, undated (Box 3 (hol), Reel 5902)
  - Oversize Clipping, 1940 (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5902)
  - Oversize Theater Poster, undated (Box 4 (sol), Reel 5902)
  - Oversize Posters, 1954-1970 (Box OV 5, Reel 5902)
  - Oversize Map of Railways Between Gettysburg and Richmond, 1939 (Box OV 5, Reel 5902)